Guide to the Benjamin Trumbull Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Benjamin Trumbull papers
1629-1867
MS 505
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
15.75
(29 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, bills and receipts, sermons, church papers, writings, and miscellanea documenting the personal life, religious career, and literary work of Benjamin Trumbull. Sermons include material on a wide range of religious, historical, political, and social topics. Correspondence and other papers include material relating to Trumbull's family life, student years, religious responsibilities, and writings on Connecticut history, divorce, and land settlement.
Trumbull, Benjamin, 1735-1820
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Walter Wetmore Holmes, 1936-1937, and subsequent purchases.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and one accession: I. Correspondence and Papers, 1629-1867. II. Sermons, 1758-1820. III. Personal Papers, 1724-1834.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence, bills and receipts, sermons, church papers, writings, and miscellanea documenting the personal life, religious career, and literary work of Benjamin Trumbull and his family. Sermons include material on a wide range of religious, historical, political, and social topics. Correspondence and other papers include material relating to Trumbull's family life, student years, religious responsibilities, and writings on Connecticut history, divorce, and land settlement. Information on the town of North Haven, Connecticut and the New England region is also included in the papers.
The Trumbull papers were willed to Yale University upon Benjamin Trumbull's death, and in 1936 Walter Wetmore Holmes made a significant addition to the papers. Other materials have been added through purchase. The papers are arranged in three series: I. Correspondence and Papers, 1629-1867; II. Sermons, 1758-1820; III. Personal Papers, 1724-1834.
SERIES I, CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS, 1629-1901, contains the correspondence of Benjamin Trumbull and other family members arranged in chronological order. The series also contains notes, student compositions and notebooks, diary entries, minutes of town meetings, church records, legal, financial, and military documents, manuscripts, wills and other papers. SERIES III, PERSONAL PAPERS, 1724-1834, also contains this type of material. Student materials include account books (folders 3 and 5) and a diary (folder 5). A small quantity of material documents Trumbull's military career (folders 22-24) and includes an account book and mileage role of a company of volunteers in 1777.
Material documenting Trumbull's religious career in North Haven, Connecticut and the work of the Congregational Church in Connecticut and Massachusetts is also organized in this series. SERIES II and III contain additional files on these subjects. Documents relating to the North Haven church include correspondence with parishioners, a diary of pastoral visits (folder 31), and a will of property to the church (folder 2). Items relating to the town of North Haven include summonses, licenses, warrants, deeds, indentures, bills, receipts, and other papers. Minutes of a 1771 town meeting (folder 17) and legal documents of Justus Bishop, Trumbull's son-in-law and a justice of the peace, are found in box three.
Additional papers in this series include a diary of Nathan Porter, 1806-1841 (folder 45), political correspondence of Chauncey Fitch Cleveland, 1835-1837 (folder 56), accounts and papers of Samuel Gray (folders 27-28; 66), an account book and memoranda of Denison Olmsted (folder 68), items relating to Daniel Pierpont's patent for a butter churn (folder 46), and statistics relating to the population of North Haven (folders 61, 67).
SERIES II, SERMONS, 1758-1820, contains a chronological arrangement of Trumbull's sermons. Isolated sermons are missing from the numbered run of material, and additional sermons are organized in SERIES III, box 28. Trumbull's copies of sermons by other ministers and notes on their sermons are arranged in SERIES III, box 26.
SERIES III, PERSONAL PAPERS, 1724-1834, contains a variety of financial documents, church-related materials, writings, and other items similar to material found in SERIES I. Trumbull's notes on sermons he attended at Yale College chapel meetings (folders 158-163, 165), papers relating to his ministry in North Haven, drafts of religious and historical writings, and other papers are arranged in this series. Files arranged under the heading "Church papers" include materials documenting the activities of many area churches (folder 129), complaints lodged against local ministers (folder 130-134), Trumbull's interest in liquor licenses (folder 136), and his historical research. Other files contain papers relating to North Haven communicants (folder 144), minutes of the General Association of the State of Connecticut (folder 145), and printed material for various church organizations.
Confessions of church members, which record public statements of sorrow for such sins as neglect of public worship, use of strong liquor, bearing false witness, and fornication (folders 149-155) provide an interesting glimpse of Trumbull's parishioners.
Benjamin Trumbull's historical writing on Connecticut and the United States is documented through drafts of his writings, research notes, and financial records relating to publication. Manuscript versions of his work on divorce (1785), the history of Connecticut (1796-1797), and land titles in Connecticut (1774) are arranged in this series.
Accession 2011-M-077 contains one manuscript by Trumbull which chronicles the Indian Wars in Connecticut written in 1767.
Additional Trumbull Papers are housed at the Beinecke Rare Book Library.
Biographical / Historical
Benjamin Trumbull was born on December 19, 1735 in Hebron, Connecticut. He graduated from Yale College in 1759 and began work as pastor for the Congregational Church of North Haven, Connecticut in 1760. He served there for sixty years, interrupted only by service as a chaplain during the Revolutionary War. He wrote thousands of sermons and several historical texts, treaties, and pamphlets. He died on February 2, 1820.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Clergy -- Connecticut; Congregational churches -- Clergy -- Biography; Divorce; Solar eclipses; Families; Connecticut -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Connecticut -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Connecticut -- Religion -- 18th century; New Haven (Conn.) -- History; North Haven (Conn.) -- History; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Sermons; Clergy; Historians; Beach, Nathaniel; Bishop, Hannah Trumbull; Clap, Thomas, 1703-1767; Daggett, Naphtali, 1727-1780; Eastman, Mary Trumbull; Lathrop, Elijah, 1724-1797; Morse, Jedidiah, 1761-1826; Pomeroy, Benjamin, 1704-1784; Stiles, Isaac, 1783-1808; Trumbull, Benjamin, 1735-1820; Tuttle, Sarah Trumbull; Wheelock, Eleazar, 1711-1779; Woodward, Martha Trumbull; Trumbull family; Congregational Church (North Haven, Conn.); Yale University -- Students
- CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS, 1629-1901; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in two sections: General, and Bills and receipts. General is arranged in chronological order. Bills and receipts is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - General
    - 1629-1774 (Box 1, Folder 1-21)
    - 1775-1800 (Box 2, Folder 22-40)
    - 1801-1867 (Box 3, Folder 41-57)
    - n. d. (Box 4, Folder 58-63)
  - Bills and receipts
    - B-F (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Bishop, David (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - G-M (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - North Haven, Connecticut (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - P-W, miscellanea (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Trumbull, Benjamin (Box 5, Folder 69-70)
- SERMONS, 1758-1820; Series II
  This series is arranged in chronological order.
  - 1758 - 1762 April (Box 6)
  - 1762 April - 1764 February (Box 7)
  - 1764 March - 1766 July (Box 8)
  - 1766 August - 1769 March (Box 9)
  - 1769 March - 1771 December (Box 10)
  - 1772 January - 1775 December (Box 11)
  - 1776 January - 1780 June (Box 12)
  - 1780 July - 1783 October (Box 13)
    General
    See also: box 14
  - 1780 September - 1784 December (Box 14, Folder 71-77)
  - 1785 January - 1787 December (Box 15, Folder 78-85)
  - 1788 January - 1792 December (Box 16, Folder 86-91)
  - 1793 January - 1798 December (Box 17, Folder 92-97)
  - 1801 - 1807 (Box 18, Folder 100-106)
  - 1808 - 1815 (Box 19, Folder 107-114)
  - 1816 - 1819 July (Box 20, Folder 115-121)
  - 1819 August - 1820 Jan, undated (Box 21, Folder 122-125)
    See also: box 28, folders 185-187 (p. 11)
- PERSONAL PAPERS, 1724-1834; Series III
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Account book, 1761-1820 (Box 22, Folder 126)
  - Church papers
    - Accounts and financial papers, 1774-1813 (Box 23, Folder 127)
    - Addresses, 1767-1814, undated (Box 23, Folder 128)
    - Cities, 1729-1796 (Box 23, Folder 129)
      - Connecticut: Branford-Watertown (Box 23, Folder 129)
      - Massachusetts: Hardwick-Westfield (Box 23, Folder 129)
    - Complaints: A-S, and correspondence, 1767-1791 (Box 23, Folder 130-132)
    - Confessions
      See: box 24, folders 149-155 (p.8)
    - Congregational Church in Connecticut:
      - Associations, 1767-1817, undated (Box 23, Folder 133)
      - Councils, 1768-1791 (Box 23, Folder 134)
    - "Doctrine of Faith and Covenant" by Isaac Stiles, annotated by Ezra Stiles, 1724, 1746 (Box 23, Folder 135)
    - Liquor licenses, 1814-1820 (Box 23, Folder 136)
    - "A List of the First Ministers in the Colonies of Connecticut and New Haven," 1629-1641, undated (Box 23, Folder 137)
    - Meeting house: specifications, etc., 1822, 1834, undated (Box 23, Folder 138)
    - Minutes, 1760-1833, undated (Box 23, Folder 139)
    - Miscellanea, 1776-1821 (Box 23, Folder 140)
    - Missionary Society, 1798-1799 (Box 23, Folder 141)
    - Mutual Improvement Society, 1779-1787, 1818 (Box 23, Folder 142)
    - Ordination of Leverett Griggs, 1833 (Box 23, Folder 143)
    - Parish records, 1762-1766 (Box 23, Folder 144)
    - Prayer meetings, 1787-1795 (Box 23, Folder 145)
    - Printed material, 1776-1832 (Box 23, Folder 146)
    - Recommendations for church membership, 1764-1813 (Box 23, Folder 147)
    - Requests for prayers, undated (Box 23, Folder 148)
  - Confessions, 1743-1807 (Box 24, Folder 149-155)
  - Musical notebook: photostats, Circa1760 (Box 25, Folder 156-157)
  - Sermons
    - General: chronological notes on sermons by Peter Buel, Thomas Clap ["President"], Naphtali Daggett, Elizur Goodrich, [John?] Graham, Elijah Lathrop, Eneas Munson, John Noyes, [STP?], Benjamin Pomeroy, Benjamin Tallmadge, Josiah Whitney, 1754-1759 (Box 26, Folder 158-159)
    - Beach, Nathaniel, undated (Box 26, Folder 160)
    - Daggett, Naphtali, 1755-1759 (Box 26, Folder 161)
    - Lathrop, Elijah, 1754-1757 (Box 26, Folder 162)
    - Pomeroy, Benjamin, 1754-1760 (Box 26, Folder 163)
    - Price, [Richard?], 1789 (Box 26, Folder 164)
    - Wheelock, Eleazar, 1759 (Box 26, Folder 165)
    - Unidentified, 1727 (Box 26, Folder 166)
  - Writings
    - General, 1759-1814 (Box 26, Folder 167-170)
    - "A Confession of Faith", undated (Box 26, Folder 171)
    - Essays: "Honesty is the Best Policy," miscellaneous, 1758-1759, undated (Box 26, Folder 172-173)
    - Funeral orations, 1761-1793, undated (Box 26, Folder 174)
    - Lecture, 1770 (Box 26, Folder 175)
    - Manuscripts
      - An Appeal to the Public, ... With Respect to the Unlawfulness of Divorces, ..., 1785 (Box 27, Folder 176)
      - A Complete History of Connecticut, ...
        - Notes, undated (Box 27, Folder 177)
        - Original manuscript, Circa1797 (Box 27, Folder 178)
        - Proposals, 1796 (Box 27, Folder 179)
      - Plea in Vindication of the Connecticut Title to the Contested Lands..., 1774 (Box 27, Folder 180)
      - New England History, miscellaneous, undated (Box 27, Folder 181)
    - Notes and fragments, undated (Box 28, Folder 182)
    - Notes on reading, undated (Box 28, Folder 183)
    - Religious questions, undated (Box 28, Folder 184)
    - Sermons, 1772-1810, undated (Box 28, Folder 185-187)
- Additional Material, 1767; Accession 2011-M-077
  - Benjamin Trumbull manuscript, "A Compendium of the Indian Wars in New England, more particularly such as the Colony of Connecticut have been concerned and active in. - New Haven, August 25th. Anno 1767." (Box 1)
    Title on Manuscript: "A Compendium of the Indian Wars in New England, more particalarly such as the Colony of Connecticut have been concerned and active in. - New Haven, August 25th. Anno 1767."